原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/hscEMyELocY
原视频发布日期：20200918
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
And today I have returned to Kerbal Space Program to do a little bit of space history.
今天我回到了坎巴拉太空计划 做一点航天历史
This is a Kerbalized clone of this Star-Raker.
这是一个坎巴拉版的Star-Raker(星球收割机)
And that's uh that's a basically a single stage to orbit aircraft which was conceived in the 1960s
这基本上就是一个在20世纪60年代构想的单级入轨飞机
and later re-investigated in detail in the 1970s.
并在70年代重新进行了详细的论证
So this was from Rockwell who ultimately built the Space Shuttle orbiter.
那么罗克韦尔公司设计了这架飞机 这家公司最终制造了航天飞机轨道器
This design obviously didn't become the Space Shuttle orbiter
很显然 这个设计没有变成航天飞机轨道器
but later in the 1970s,
但在20世纪70年代后期
the US was very interested in the possibility of building a network of 60 giant solar power satellites in space.
美国很有兴趣在太空中建立一个由60颗巨型太阳能卫星组成的网络
And Star-Raker was conceived as a vehicle that could make that happen.
而Star-Raker被认为是实现这一目标的工具
Something that could launch to space, drop off cargo, return and keep flying.
它可以发射到太空 放下货物 返回并继续飞行
spaceflighthistory.blogspot.com/2020/09/star-raker-1978.html
So anyway a lot of this episode is actually going to be based around a blog post by Davis S Portree
那么无论如何 这一集的很多内容 都是围绕着Davis S Portree的一篇博客文章展开的
who I've admired for a long time.
这人我敬佩他很久了
He's been really good at doing space history.
在航天史方面 他真的很厉害
whenever I do space history, I inevitably find blog posts by him on the exact subject.
每当我做航天史的时候 不可避免地 我都会发现他(已经)写过相关主题的博文了
I'm sure he'd appreciate it if you backed him on patreon because this is pretty much his main job.
我相信如果你在patreon上支持他 他会很感激 因为这差不多是他的主要工作
So yes in october of 1977,
那么 在1977年10月
a team of Rockwell international engineers got together to study this Space Raker design.
罗克韦尔国际工程师团队聚集在一起 研究这个Space Raker的设计
It was going to be 100m long, 93m wide and it would have carried about 90t to low Earth orbit.
它将会有100米长 93米宽 近地轨道运载能力大约90吨
They anticipated it would need over a thousand flights per year to support the space power system program
为了支持太空能源系统的计划 他们预计每年需要超过一千次的飞行
that would mean like one launch every eight hours.
这意味着每8小时发射一次
For this it could actually operate from a regular runway.
为此 它实际上可以从一条普通的跑道上运行
They would obviously need to supply the liquid hydrogen, the engines needed
显然 (跑道虽然普通 但是)他们需要提供发动机需要的燃料 液氢
but other than that they could operate anywhere in the world.
但除此之外 他们可以在世界的任何地方运行
And this was of course seen in it as an advantage
而这当然被看作是一个优势
because they could pick up hardware from airports all over the US, integrate and then take it to orbit.
因为他们可以从美国各地的机场搭载设备 整合后再送入轨道
Now for a launch to orbit it would also have to be loaded with liquid oxygen
现在 要想发射到轨道上 还得加注液氢
so that plus the cargo would bring its mass to about 2000 tons.
那么再加上货物 将使其质量达到2000吨左右
To get this much off the runway, they would have an extra set of landing gear
为了让这么多的货物离开跑道 这架飞机将配备一套额外的起落架
which would be attached and then dropped after takeoff so that that would then be recovered.
起飞前接上 起飞后再扔掉 这样就可以回收起落架了
Now the jet engines there were 10 of them and they were basically magic.
那么 飞机上搭载了10台喷气式发动机 但这些发动机基本上都充满魔法(笑)
They would start out as turbo jets and turned into with with afterburners.
一开始是涡轮喷气发动机 然后使用后燃器
They would switch mode and ultimately become ram jets
之后切换模式 并最终成为冲压式喷气发动机
and they would work, producing thrust all the way up to about mach 6.
发动机工作并产生推力 一直到6马赫左右
And it reaches the speed of mach 6 accelerating through a climb.
通过爬升加速 飞机将达到6马赫的速度
So the launch trajectory had it reaching mach 6 at about 29 km of altitude. That's about 18mi about 100000ft.
那么发射轨道是在29公里(18英里/10万英尺)的高度达到6马赫的速度
And by then of course, the air does start to get thinner.
当然 到那时 空气开始变稀薄
And that's the point where they turn on the three main engines.
这时 三台主引擎点火
These are hydrogen oxygen rocket engines and they generate combined thrust of about 1500 tons.
这些是氢氧火箭发动机 总推力约为1500吨(单台推力约500吨)
Now it's worth noting that the propellant for these jet engines is stored inside these very large wings
值得注意的是 这些喷气发动机的推进剂 储存在这些非常大的机翼里
and they have diagrams of the exact tank design.
而且他们有确切的储箱设计图
Whereas the three rocket engines,
而三台火箭发动机
they draw their propellant their hydrogen from inside the aircraft fuselage.
从机身内部获得液氧和液氢
So at this point it's about mach 7.2. It shuts down the jet engines
到了差不多7.2马赫时 喷气式发动机关机
and closes the air intakes for aerodynamics and now it's entirely on rocket power.
为了更好的空气动力外形 飞机关闭了进气道 并完全靠火箭动力
it's about one third of the way to orbital velocity so it has to keep firing that.
此时 它的轨道速度只有三分之一 所以必须继续点火加速
Lifting itself out of the atmosphere to an altitude of about 340 miles.
将自己从大气层中抬升到大约547公里的高度
Now when the main engine's shut down, it isn't in a proper orbit.
当主引擎关闭时 它并不在一个正确的轨道上
It has an apogee which is well outside the atmosphere but its perigee is still inside the atmosphere.
远地点在大气层外 但近地点仍在大气层内
So it cruises around for about another 45 minutes until it reaches apogee
所以在轨道上滑行了大约45分钟 直到到达远地点为止
and then circularizes the trajectory using a third set of engines.
然后用第三组发动机圆化轨道
It had a pair of orbital maneuvering system engines
它有一对轨道机动系统发动机
and these are presumably burning hypergolic propellants of some sort.
而这些发动机大概是使用某种自燃推进剂
Once in orbit
一旦进入轨道
those orbital maneuvering thrusters would be used to rendezvous with its target and unload its cargo.
就使用轨道机动推进器与目标交会 并卸载货物
So the cargo bay in the Star-Raker was built into the main fuselage.
所以Star-Raker的货舱是建在主机身内的
Unlike the Space Shuttle which had cargo bay doors on top,
不像航天飞机那样 货舱门放在顶部
Rockwell felt that this was a point of structural weakness in the Shuttle design
罗克韦尔认为 这是航天飞机设计中的一个结构弱点
so they came up with a different design.
所以他们提出了一个不同的设计
The cargoes in the center fuselage is behind the cockpit here.
机身中央的货物在驾驶舱后面
The crew would move to the back of the crew compartment
而乘员会移动到乘员舱的后方
where they had windows that looked into the cargo bay
他们通过那里的窗户可以看到货舱
and then the entire nose would hinge around and move out of the way providing access to the cargo.
然后整个机头就使用铰链打开 给货物提供进出的通道
So this particular cargo, the storage mechanism wasn't particularly well detailed in the studies.
那么搭载(太阳能电站)这种特殊的货物 使用的存储机制 在研究中并没有特别详细的说明
But it was understood that if they were to dock with a structure, they would be doing it in this mode.
但据了解 如果他们要与一个结构对接 就会以这种模式进行
So it's conceivable that a large amount of maneuvering and docking
所以可以想象 会有大量的机动和对接的工作
would be carried out with the pilots essentially looking out their left window at the docking.
此时 驾驶员会从左窗向对接处张望
So yeah in this case I've just got a single payload in there.
那么 在这里 我只搭载了一个载荷
We're gonna slide it forwards and release it.
我们要把它向前滑动并释放它
And I'm just gonna point out for the Kerbal players here.
对于坎巴拉玩家我要提一句
This is actually a separate craft file from the other object
(带有货舱的这艘飞船)实际上是另一个设计文件里的
because I couldn't make them fly separately.
因为我无法让它进行飞行
The aerodynamics didn't work with the hinge and the nose kept on falling off.
(游戏的)空气动力学与铰链不协调 机头一直在掉
But in this case yes we have this beautiful little satellite being deployed.
但不管怎么说 这个美丽的小卫星得到了部署
My design also has the cargo bay being significantly shorter
我的设计中 货舱也明显短了很多
just because I messed up to be honest.
说实话只是因为我搞砸了
This hinge loading mechanism would of course be used on the ground
当然 这种铰链式装载机构也会在地面上使用
and you can see several images
你可以看到几个图片
where they have these planes, a Star-Raker
图片里有一些飞机 也有一个Star-Raker
essentially rolled up with their nose inside a giant transparent clean room on the ground.
基本上是在地面上一个巨大的透明洁净室里 进行弯折机头的操作
So once the payload was deployed, they would fold the cockpit back into place.
一旦有效载荷完成部署 就把驾驶舱折回原位
And they would prepare for return to Earth.
然后准备返回地球
By this point they've obviously burned most of the propellant
这时 飞机显然已经用掉了大部分的推进剂
and based upon, you know, interactions with NASA,
并且根据开发团队与NASA的交流
it looks like the mass of the vehicle would about be about 330 metric tons without any propellant.
除去推进剂 也就是这艘航天器的干质量大约有330吨
Of course at this point they still have propellant on board because they have to perform the deorbit burn
当然在这里 他们还是有些推进剂的 因为要进行离轨点火
and then they also have leftover hydrogen
同样 他们也有剩余的液氢
which they're going to use for cross range when they get back into the atmosphere.
当他们回到大气层时 飞机可以使用液氢进行机动
Because of its large wings, it would actually have a much easier re-entry than the Space Shuttle.
得益于它的大机翼 它再入大气层时会比航天飞机更加舒适
It was estimated that peak g-forces would be about 2.3 gravity because the wings were so large.
据估计 由于机翼很大 最大过载只有2.3倍的重力
For the thermal protection system there were two options proposed.
对于热保护系统 他们提出了两种方案
One was to use the low conductivity high temperature ceramic tiles that were used on the space station(口胡).
一种是使用航天飞机上的低热传导性耐高温陶瓷砖
The other was a metal heat shield
另一种是金属隔热板
where you would have sheets of metal with posts, pretty you know, standing it out from the hull
这种薄薄的金属隔热板将使用支架安装在船体外边
and inside the gap you would have thermal blankets inside.
同时在缝隙中填充隔热毯
So in some of the low temperature areas you could get away with titanium, aluminium.
那么 在一些低温区域 可以使用钛或者铝来处理热量
In other areas they would need something well they describe it as a super alloy.
而在高温区域 则使用他们所谓的超级合金
Compared to the Space Shuttle, they had a higher lift to drag ratio.
与航天飞机相比 这架飞机有着更高的升阻比
So they could get away with lower loads and lower temperatures.
所以飞机在再入时经受的过载更低 温度更低
And by the time they were developing this,
在他们研发这个项目的时候
they had already developed the technology to actually do computer models
实际已经开发出制作计算机模型的技术
which weren't available in the early days of Space Shuttle development.
而这在航天飞机研制初期是没有的
Like the Space Shuttle it would be a glider for most of re-entry.
和航天飞机一样 它在重返大气层的大部分时间里都是滑翔机
As it slowed down and became more aerodynamic,
随着它的速度减慢 而气动效应(随着大气密度提高)变得显著
it would begin to use S-turns to control the energy and try to make sure it ends up near the launch site.
它将开始使用S型转弯来控制能量 并试图确保它最终到达发射场附近
But unlike the Space Shuttle, this had propellant leftover
但与航天飞机不同的是 它有剩余的推进剂
and the engines were designed to come back online and help it reach whatever landing site it could.
而且发动机被设计成可以重复点火 使之进行一定的机动来选择着陆场
The designers had other plans for this large cross-range capability.
对于这种机动能力 开发人员曾有其他的使用计划
They envisaged early on that it would be able to take off from Florida
他们很早就设想它能从佛罗里达州起飞
and then instead of immediately going into orbit in a 20 degree inclination orbit
然后不立即进入20(28)度倾角的轨道
it would head south towards the equator for several hours until it was at zero latitude
而是向南朝赤道方向前进几个小时 直到零纬度
and then it would perform its takeoff into orbit.
然后再进行入轨飞行
And that would leave the hardware in a zero degree inclination orbit
这将使设备(有效载荷)处于零度倾角的轨道上
and this wouldn't actually help it launch that much more into orbit
而实际上这种机动并不能帮助它提高有效载荷能力(因为大气内机动会消耗不少燃料)
but more importantly since this was for a plan to put geostationary solar power satellites up there,
但更重要的是 因为计划里是为了把太阳能卫星送入地球静止轨道(GEO)
it would mean that launching that hardware into geostationary orbit would have required less fuel.
所以这意味着 卫星(从地球静止转移轨道/GTO)进入GEO所花费的燃料会减少
Therefore they would have had to launch less hardware overall into orbit.
这样 卫星的发射质量就可以减少
But ultimately after consultation with NASA, they decided to drop this plan.
但最终在与NASA协商后 他们决定放弃这个计划
First of all they tried to save it by reducing the mass of the aircraft at launch
首先他们试图通过减少飞机发射时的质量来解决问题
and then only loading liquid oxygen in flight at the equator.
后来又改成只在赤道(起飞)的飞行中加注液氧 (而在大气层内转场飞行中不加注)
But ultimately they gave up on the whole idea
但最终他们还是放弃了这个想法
and they decided everything would be launching into a 28 degree orbit.
他们决定将所有的东西都发射到倾角28度的轨道上
Either way the whole thing was supposed to return to a runway
不管怎么说 整架飞机都会返回到跑道上
and with minimal checkouts be able to be relaunched.
而且重新发射前只需要极少量的检查
They would land it, load the new hardware, attach the extra gear for the ground launch
他们将降落它 装载新的设备 为从地面起飞安装额外的起落架
and then it would take off and head back to space and keep on doing this
然后它就会起飞 回到太空 并持续这样的发射
and building out solar power satellites in orbit.
之后建造出在轨的太阳能卫星
While this study was performed in 1978,
虽然这项研究是在1978年进行的
they didn't envisage this whole thing ramping up and starting until like 2000
他们设想中这一切只会在2000年之后才开始
which is probably why they expected liquid hydrogen to be available at basically any air airport.
这大概就是为什么他们会期待每个机场里基本都提供液氢
But it also gave them two decades to solve their problems
但这也给了他们二十年的时间来解决他们的问题
like how to make their engines work all the way up to mach 7 without melting due to the input air.
比如如何让他们的发动机一直工作到7马赫而不因为(高温)空气的吸入而融化
Now obviously the study never went anywhere.
现在很明显 这项研究从来没有任何进展
It was never translated into actual flying equipment
它从未被转化为实际的飞行设备
but the idea of the single stage to orbit space plane using multi-mode engines has never quite gone away.
但使用变循环发动机的单级入轨航天飞机的想法一直没有完全消失
And right now the best example is the Skylon,
而现在最好的例子就是云霄塔
a space plane propelled by the SABRE engine, synergistic air breathing rocket engine.
它使用SABRE发动机 全称混合模式吸气火箭发动机
A rocket engine that early in the flight can suck its air from the atmosphere
一种在飞行初期就能从大气层中吸气的火箭发动机
and then once it gets higher up it can switch over to internal liquid oxygen
一旦它升到更高的地方 它就可以(把氧化剂)切换到内部的液氢
and carry itself all the way to space.
并一路运行到飞机入轨
But I will have to talk about that in some detail some other time.
不过 我得改天再详细说说这个问题
For now this was Star-Raker.
暂时而言 这期视频就讲Star-Raker
Thanks to Davis Portree for his work on documenting space history
感谢Davis Portree在记录航天历史方面的工作
and giving me lots of stuff to read.
并给我很多东西来阅读
Definitely check out his blog, you know, support him.
一定要去看看他的博客 去支持他
And maybe we'll feature some more of his research in the future.
也许未来我会制作更多关于他的研究的视频
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]